A Guide to the Papers of Anne Spencer and the Spencer Family, 1829, 1864-2007
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Manuscripts and Poems (Box-folder 17:7-22:55)
  - Manuscripts arranged by beginning line (Box-folder 18:1-18:39)
    - n.d. Manuscript beginning "Madam, for this moment you may call me nigger, for the moment I permit…" (Box-folder 18:11))
    - n.d. Manuscript beginning "Mr. Lippman's segregated sortie into my town" (Box-folder 18:12))
    - [post 1941 Jan] Manuscript beginning "The Negro child's book is our street" (Box-folder 18:13))
    - n.d. Manuscript beginning "Nobody can run you if you don't run" (Box-folder 18:14))
    - ca. 1941-1945 Manuscript beginning "On my way to work this morning, I stopped for a look into a bright, tho serious world" (Box-folder 18:15))
    - n.d. Manuscript beginning "Out in our Creator's universe" concerning Franklin Delano Roosevelt (Box-folder 18:16))
    - n.d. Manuscript beginning "People who search your anatomy for a place where the skin is off" (Box-folder 18:17))
    - n.d. Manuscript beginning "Personally, I have everything I want, except, maybe, enough spring onions" (Box-folder 18:18))
    - n.d. Manuscript beginning "Poems walk right out of your mind in such a queer way… in such queer times," Also includes a note in the back on the "morality of American parents" (Box-folder 18:19))
    - n.d. Manuscript beginning "A rosy moon hangs over Venice" and on the back of sheet "If I could hope in the years from now" (Box-folder 18:20))
    - [post 1963 Sep] Manuscript beginning "Speaking of intermarriage" (Box-folder 18:21))
    - n.d. Manuscript beginning "Tell me while I wait" (Box-folder 18:22))
    - n.d. Manuscript beginning "That the Stars Were Made For Man to Climb" (Box-folder 18:23))
    - n.d. Manuscript beginning "There is this stark likeness between our America and Russia after their serfdom" (Box-folder 18:24))
    - n.d. Manuscript beginning "These, awhile have been my joy; but, instead of these the raging loneliness of the lion whose mate died" (Box-folder 18:25))
    - [post 1960 Dec] Manuscript beginning "These streets, the honey clay are too expensive" (Box-folder 18:26))
    - n.d. Manuscript beginning "They who kept the black buck at stud" (Box-folder 18:27))
    - n.d. Manuscript beginning "This business of going to heaven is obsolete" (Box-folder 18:28))
    - n.d. Manuscript beginning "Time, the aged painter brush this clay, the stones - stroke by stroke, memorable" written in pencil on a board (Box-folder 18:29))
    - n.d. Manuscript beginning "To sit right here in a Kantian seat" (Box-folder 18:30))
    - n.d. Manuscript beginning "The universe-maker took time out from his prodigious job to punish" (Box-folder 18:31))
    - [post 1960 Jun] Manuscript beginning "We are your hands" (Box-folder 18:32))
    - n.d. Manuscript beginning "We could skip Plato Seneca and Onassis - Er, I mean Aristotle" (Box-folder 18:33))
    - n.d. Manuscript beginning "We moderners are so afraid of purpleness" (Box-folder 18:34))
    - n.d. Manuscript beginning "When I am gone and you are here" (Box-folder 18:35))
    - n.d. Manuscript beginning "Woman's land is the country of sublimation" (Box-folder 18:36))
    - [post 1965 Jun] Manuscript beginning "The year 1965 seemed an especially good year for the death of imminent and unique men" (Box-folder 18:37))
    - n.d. Manuscript beginning "You are still young enough to think of me as a woman sere - out worn" (Box-folder 18:38))
    - n.d. Manuscript beginning "You Earth you poor strong scallion" (Box-folder 18:39))
  - Topical Manuscripts with no titles, arranged by subject (Box-folder 18:40-20:2)
    - 1946-1973, n.d. Manuscripts concerning A Topics, including: abortion and illegitimate births; accidents and chance; African-Americans ("Negroes"); age/aging; aliens; ambition (greatness); apathy; art; an author (Box-folder 18:40))
    - 1964-1972 Manuscripts concerning Autobiography and Family History (Box-folder 18:41))
    - n.d. Manuscripts concerning Autobiography and Family History - Notebooks, tablet 3 has a partial typescript transcript in red ink (Box-folder 18:42))
    - n.d. Manuscripts concerning B Topics, including: Bible (also includes mind vs. spirit); body cleansing; books (including one with the additional topics of remedial education and the evil of money; another concerning National Library Week) (Box-folder 18:43))
    - 1941-1964, n.d. Manuscripts concerning C Topics, including: calamus (also describes dream about skulls); cannibalism; cats; charity; child; China; the christs of this earth; the city; Civil War; compassion; the Congo; courtship; cowardice (oversize); creatures; crime; Crimea; culture (Box-folder 18:44))
    - n.d. Manuscripts concerning Civil Rights and Integration (Box-folder 18:45))
    - [post 1957], n.d. Manuscripts concerning D Topics, including: dead; dentist; detection; dogs; dreams (Box-folder 18:46))
    - [post 1971], n.d. Manuscripts concerning E Topics, including: economics; England; equality; evil, executives (Box-folder 18:47))
    - [post 1961-64], n.d. Manuscripts concerning Education and Learning, including the impact of slavery, schools in Lynchburg (Box-folder 18:48))
    - [post 1945], n.d. Manuscripts concerning F Topics, including: fairy tale; the farmer; feelings for or against people you don't know; forgetting; Francisco; friendship (Box-folder 18:49))
    - [post 1932-69], n.d. Manuscripts concerning G Topics, including: gardens; generosity; gentleman vs. man; German empire; gifts; good sense; Greece (ancient); grammar; greed; grief; growth (Box-folder 18:50))
    - [post 1952-64], n.d. Manuscripts concerning H Topics, including: Haiti, mentioning Forbes, William A. White and Hoover; happiness; the hate of old men; hatreds of Europe; healthy bodies; heaven; "razing" hell; history books; honesty; household furnishing; humaneness; humanity (also includes generic references to "man"; humanity as true and false liars; humility; humor; husband and wife (Box-folder 18:51))
    - [post 1959], n.d. Manuscripts concerning I-K Topics, including: ice and fire comparison; illiteracy; iron curtain: kindness; KKK (Box-folder 18:52))
    - [post 1923-57], n.d. Manuscripts concerning L Topics, including: ladies, language; Lidice; a lie; life; love; love of mankind vs. the single man; love vs. lust; Lynchburg, Virginia (as compared to Roanoke) (Box-folder 19:1))
    - [post 1941-64], n.d. Manuscripts concerning Literature and Libraries, including David L. Cohn's book Love in America; Charles Dickens; Negro Caravan; reading; Ida Tarbell; Tolstoy; Notes on the State of Virginia by Thomas Jefferson (includes mention of enslaving Indians and the prodigy, Phillipa Schuyler); Laura Jean Libby; Alfred, Lord Tennyson; Melville; Allan Tate; John Donne, Carlyle, and Piers Plowman; Nathaniel Hawthorne's Wonder Book; Whittier and Longfellow; William Faulkner and Requiem for a Nun, [James Branch?] Cabell (Box-folder 19:2))
    - n.d. Manuscripts concerning Literature and Libraries, including Dante's Fires, and Uncle Tom and Uncle Remus written on the inside covers of a three ring notebook (oversize) (Box 19)
    - [post 1941-66], n.d. Manuscripts concerning M Topics, including: machine, thinking with; man needing two hearts, body and soul; marauders; the Marstons; the matrix (die and fermentation); meeting again in another world; the mind; missions; money; moon; morality; moron vs. a fool; murder and double-standard convictions; music; mysteries or "whodunits" (Box-folder 19:3))
    - [1939-1944], n.d. Manuscripts concerning N Topics, including: National Airmen Association; Native Americans; nature; "the Negro"; Newark, New Jersey; newspapers (Box-folder 19:4))
    - [post 1944-72], n.d. Manuscript concerning P Topics, including: passementerie; pastors; peace symbol; pessimists vs. optimists; "pillar of fire"; poets in "whodunits"; poetry anthologies; Poland and Stalin; politeness; the poor; portents; preachers; pregnancy; prejudice; pride; psychology; purpose (Box-folder 19:5))
    - [post 1926-66], n.d. Manuscripts concerning People, including: Mrs. Robert A. Abernathy; "Mr. Cabell and Mr. Rutledge"; Chelembwe (African native); comparing King David of the Old Testament and Senator [Carter Glass] of Virginia (also mentions a Mrs. Wilson who "died when she did because I prayed for her death"); Jefferson Davis; Hugh Downs; fable of Ralph Waldo Emerson about the mountain and the squirrel; Munroe Fox; Henry Garrett, Ph.D.; Jenny Geddes; Ellen Glasgow; Josepha Hale; Adolf Hitler and evil; Andrew Jackson; Andrew Jackson and others, including Henry Clay, Luther, Calhoun, Nat Turner, Bledsoe of the University of Virginia, and John [Brown?]; funeral of the Reverend Vernon Johns; [Georgia Douglas Johnson?]; James Weldon Johnson; Immanuel Kant; [John?] Kennedy; Coretta [King?]; Charles Lindbergh; Belva Lockwood; [Michelangelo?]; Robert Moses (1888-1981); the Nortons; A. Philip Randolph; Franklin D. Roosevelt and Shenandoah National Park; Anna Russell; Ignatius Sancho; Ellery Sedgwick, editor Atlantic Monthly Magazine, 1908-1938; [Sam?] Sheppard; Mrs. Shuey, Robert Browning, and Alexander Hamilton; Alec Simpson; Jan Christiaan Smuts, holism, and evolution; Stalin; the suicide of George Sterling, "this fatalist pupil of Bierce," by poison during a visit of H.L. Mencken to the Bohemian Club in San Francisco ([1926 Nov?]; Strom Thurmond; Harriet Tubman; Rebecca West; Walter White; Mrs. Woodrow Wilson; Mr. Young's column (Box-folder 19:6))
    - [post 1942-71], n.d. Manuscripts concerning Politics, including: classless society; Federalists, Hamilton, and Pushkin; women and politics; Franklin D. Roosevelt and [Harry F. Byrd, Sr.] (Box-folder 19:7))
    - [post 1919-60], n.d. Manuscripts concerning R Topics, including: race (on back of paper has peace and war); racism (includes mention of visit of General Carlos P. Romulo, aide to President Manuel L. Quezon to Lynchburg); racism and repression in Lynchburg; racism and fascism link; reading, including children reading; revolution; Rubifoam dental products (Box-folder 19:8))
    - [post 1923-64], n.d. Manuscripts concerning Religion and Metaphysical Topics (Box-folder 19:9))
    - [post 1967-71], n.d. Manuscripts concerning S Topics, including: seeing like a child; semantics; service and friendship; shame; silence; sin, the soul; the South; speciousness, our mortal enemy; spring; stable (Box-folder 19:10))
    - 1932, [post 1950], n.d. Manuscripts concerning Slavery (Box-folder 19:11))
    - [post 1956-60], n.d. Manuscripts concerning T Topics, including: tailor with a need to shudder; teaching (with humorous story); technology and science; television; television show, The Ghost and Mrs Muir; thought; touchstones; truth (Box-folder 19:12))
    - [post 1967]-1974, n.d. Manuscripts concerning U-V Topics, including: Vega star; violence; Virginia (Box-folder 19:13))
    - [post 1929-63], n.d. Manuscripts concerning W-Z Topics, including: "wailing"; the war effort and race relations (World War II); West Virginia; the will, womanhood (Southern); woman of Southern extraction (also includes brief notes about the dead, Robert [Ralph?] Abernathy; women and feminism; women (African-American); women and politics; words; work; workers in the defense plants during World War II; World War II and the Japanese; and "Zilla" (Box-folder 19:14))
    - n.d. Manuscripts discussing the concept of "a different country" and the poet, including ideas about each poet occupying a different country of the mind, the local poetry club being a "white country of Sahara-like aridity too pretentious for real poetry neither white nor black," apparent suggestions for a book title for someone, such as Black in Every Hue, since black retains every color and white omits every color, and a mention of her poem "At the Carnival" (Box-folder 19:15))
    - 1921-[post 1972], n.d. Manuscript Fragments, (1 of 2 folders) (Box-folder 19:16))
    - [post 1946-73], n.d. Manuscript Fragments, (2 of 2 folders) (Box-folder 20:1))
    - [post 1966], n.d. Manuscript Fragments mentioning individuals, including: Katherine Chapin; "Hallie"; artist Jean Helion; Charles Lynch and the Reverend Haywood Robinson (former pastor of Diamond Hill Baptist Church, Lynchburg); A.P. (a college president), Roland Hayes, Cecil Rhodes, Dr. [Jameson?], and Martin Johnson; Allen Tate; the Virgin Mary (Box-folder 20:2))
  - Dated Notebooks (Box-folder 20:3-20:12)
    - 1927, 1959-72, n.d. Notebook, consisting of an actual diary which has entries in ink by someone, probably for the year 1927, and to which Anne Spencer added her own material. Spencer's material will be cited by the "date" on the page of the entry, although it is assumed that will not be the correct date for her manuscript entries. Notes are organized by the "month" of the entries. Many of the entries appear to have been written at the height of the struggle for Civil Rights and integration. (Box-folder 20:3))
      On the title page and its verso, she writes concerning the Constitution and slavery.
      In the main part of the diary, section for January, Anne Spencer writes about the Prodigal Son (January 1); the Byrds, Georgia's U.S. Senator [Richard B.] Russell, Jr., difficulty of African-Americans in dealing with "our appearance on this continent factually" (January 2); "Virginia as Narcissus" (January 3); a list of people and concepts placed in a credit column or a debit column (January 4); Notes for "Virginia as Narcissus" discussing racism and including a quote about her preference in epithets, "I choose Nigger to dear darky. Nigger given a 25 % to 50 % chance can defend me and himself but a darky is a moral queer" (January 5-11, and possibly more); the NAACP and her monetary involvement (January 11-12); mentions Roland Hayes (1887-1977) and the famous incident in the Georgia shoe store (January 13); Governor James Lindsay Almond's election, the Acts of Assembly for 1852-1854, "to read it makes one hope as in primate evolution that we have ascended from the apes," and the caste system in India compared with America (January 14-15); integration (January 16); Lindsay Almond's speech, the Byrd machine (January 18); takes issue with the statement of a Southern religionist Governor [Richard B. Russell, Jr.] teaching a "businessman's Bible class" on the radio, "only the Anglo-Saxon has exercised the art of gardening!" (January 19-21); the vanity of the state of Virginia and the editorial critical of local [Lynchburg?] Negro leadership (January 22); hatred spread world-wide through the threat of annihilation (January 23); mentions Friend to Friend: A Candid Exchange between Pearl S. Buck and Carlos P. Romulo (1958) (January 24); Narcissus (January 25); "Virginia as Narcissus or the Southern Mind" (January 26-28); Acts of the General Assembly of Virginia, passed 1853-1854 (January 29-30); the fascist campaign against the Jews and the idea of monotheism and quote from her poem "White Things" "and fling in the face of God with all your might Man-maker, make white" (January 31-February 1)
      Entries by Anne Spencer under the February section include: a story from Thinking Black by Dan Crawford and examples of ways "the Southern mind has shown its determination to reconcrete slavedom polices" through Plessy v Ferguson and Jim Crowism (February 1); quotes from Raymond Moley about empathy and praises Franklin Roosevelt (February 2); discusses public schools, epithets, Sequoia, and John Trumball, tutor at Yale (February 3); warns that history must be read with caution, mentioning Palgrave, William Byrd, and John Smith, until you get to Ellen Glasgow, "her fiction is the very essence of these new world folk in their dominating situation" and James Branch Cabell (February 4); Spencer asks the question, since public schools are equal, why not mix the white children into the equalized colored schools? (February 5); quotes from her poem "White Things" (February 6); discusses Faulkner in Japan and his comments about Japan, loyalty, the truth, and integration (February 7-9); U.S. Senator Jacob Javits on integration (February 9); Alexander Pushkin and Russian literature (February 10-13); credits the African slaves and indentured debtors and criminals with producing the American nation (February 11); mention of Anselm and Arthur Koestler (February 12); describes Hodding Carter with a good face and open countenance and comments about the South filling "the cities of our land with the ghettoes and explosions of the Harlem Projects" … with no mixed jobs or places without a sign "white ladies colored women" (February 15-16); the campaign of the governor in 1959 with his vicious comments about African-Americans (February 16-17); the divisions of white society and a few lines of poetry:
      Delicate distant shepherdess
      And hours that run
      Held by clouds
      From the blazing sun (February 18)
      Comments about Oliver Cromwell, Macaulay, Milton, and Harry Byrd (February 19-20); Mississippi Senator J.C. Stinnett, Robert Owen, integration conflict (February 21); Wendell Wilkie and Adlai Stevenson (February 25); hypocrisy of the South, "The South's anxious, eager even, willingness to give away an [intangible] Jesus in a far-flung all inclusive way but to keep for themselves His sheep on a thousand hills, the loaves and fishes, the hire without the work, the good part, supper in the upper room" (February 28).
      Entries by Anne Spencer under the March section include: some material for the John Brown poem (March 1); a draft of her poem "Any Wife to Any Husband A Derived Poem" written on August 1972 (March 2); more material for her John Brown poem (March 4, 6, 7); paean to Abraham Lincoln (March 8-9); material for "Le Roi Meets Lincoln" or "When Abraham Lincoln Met Leroy Jones" (March 9-11); begins a manuscript piece with "There is nothing more boring than too much connubial bliss" (March 11-12). The rest of March has ink entries from the unknown original owner of the diary, but no Anne Spencer.
      Entries by Anne Spencer under the April section include: states "the wild men; the red men, the black men were the foundation of their own calamity and of the white supremacy" in the New World (April 14); education (April 16); David Lee, H.L. Mencken, and public schools (April 17); Chaucer, Lowell Thomas, "yellow peril" (April 19); and "An Informal Talk to Myself on Virginia as Narcissus," part of it with the date June 1959 (April 20-21, 25-28).
      Entries by Anne Spencer under the May section include: "Negro Attitude Toward Each Other" and comment by Corra Harris (May 9); [Gullah?] language (May 19); material for her John Brown poem (May 21); "Appomattox was a victory for the South" (May 24); and references to Senator Jacob Javits and Clifford Dowdey, and a more in-depth discussion of an interview between James Weldon Johnson and Editor Douglas Southall Freeman when they talked about the Racial Integrity Law (May 26-28).
      There were no entries by Anne Spencer in June or July.
      Entries by Anne Spencer under the August section include: the missing record in the ages of mankind is that of the Negro (August 4); the sword of Jesus a weapon against cruelty (August 8); and more material for her John Brown poem (August 12-27).
      Entries by Anne Spencer under the September section include: "The Ebony Laddy" (September 26-27).
      There were no entries by Anne Spencer in October.
      Entries by Anne Spencer under the November section include: A family story about Edward A. Spencer and his propensity for finding useful articles, articulated by his daughter, "She learned, she said her first and only precept in chemistry: 'nothing in nature is lost.' That axiom was easy, she knew where all the would- have-been-lost things got to. Pop found them in his itinerary and brought them home." (November 10-11).
      Entries by Anne Spencer under the December section include: reasons why some lack possessions (December 4); more material for her John Brown poem ((December 5, 7, 9); "being somebody" (December 8); new breed of golfers, dated August 1972 (December 9); H.L. Mencken's quote about liars (December 10); integration of public schools (December 11-12); America and sexual promiscuity, dated October 15, 1970 (December 14); dreams and two greatest peoples in the world, the Englishman and the Hebrew (December 15); slavery, hatred (December 17); slave owners and the value of slaves (December 18-19); Emerson, and England's finest hour (December 20); the essence of religion (December 21); "Everything happens for the best" (December 23); [Fair Employment Practices Commission?] (December 27); America Firsters and proles (December 30); mention of Kathleen Norris (1880-1966), Charles Lindbergh, and Kelland (December 31).
      Entries by Anne Spencer in the Memoranda Pages include: Civil Rights and the right to vote; hasty pudding aristocracy; and Robert E. Lee, on the inside back cover.
    - 1936, n.d. Notebook, has "Comments and Poetry" and Spencer's address written on front cover; inside front cover, Spencer writes about Archibald Rutledge, of "Hampton," near Charleston, South Carolina, "This is the Rutledge who writes of the 'mess that is Harlem.' Below we see 'Prince' on horseback. In an American magazine article Rutledge makes Prince out as having more sense, more poise, and a finer heart and a keener brain than he himself has; yet Prince's supreme chance for all his days is to sit momentarily ahorse and have his pitcher took. And too, that is why Harlem was born!"; other items following (in order of their appearance) include: a poem "From Half-past thirty"; a story about Zilla and childhood, beginning "Every childhood is a secret thing in a public place."; "Dialogue for Cards"; statement that after the discovery of coal in West Virginia, the young men of Virginia and Pennsylvania were sent off to make their fortunes in West Virginia; "The Illusion Machine" and other references to vision or images; poem "Garden Incident" (see also "Po' Little Lib"); poem "Invocation for a Christmas Baby"; comment "To lack a sense of humor is to be forever denied the pure Truth" with a poem about humor and laughter on the same page; draft of a letter from Spencer to "Darling C & G" about her trip to [New York?], recipe for a drink she had there, trouble with Chauncey, who wanted to go to aviation school, and couldn't get a job (October 18, 1936); names; and a draft of a letter to [James Weldon Johnson?] about his "perfect" book [Selected Poems?]. (Box-folder 20:4))